[MUSIC]
[음악]
Well let's look at an algorithm for doing clustering that uses this
클러스터 중심과의 거리만을 기준으로 삼는
metric of just looking at the distance to the cluster center.
클러스터링 알고리즘을 살펴보죠
Okay, so here, we see the data that we're gonna wanna cluster.
여기 클러스터링하고 싶은 데이터가 있습니다
And this algorithm, which is called the k-means algorithm,
k-means라 불리는 이 알고리즘은
starts by assuming that you are gonna end up with k clusters.
k 클러스터가 있다는 가정부터 시작합니다
So you specify the number of clusters ahead of time.
그러니까 클러스터의 수를 미리 지정하지요
So the reason the algorithm is called k-means is we have k clusters, and
알고리즘이 k-means이라 불리는 이유는 k 클러스터가 있고
we're looking at the means of the clusters, just the cluster centers,
각 샘플을 클러스터로 할당할 때
when we're assigning points to the different clusters.
클러스터의 평균인 클러스터 중심을 보기 때문입니다
Okay, so let's talk about how we initialize the algorithm.
알고리즘을 어떻게 초기화할지 알아보죠
So the first thing we do is we just one example.
처음으로는
There are many ways to initialize where we put the cluster centers.
클러스터 중심을 어디에 놓을지 초기화 하는 방법이 여러 개 있는데
We will talk about these things more in-depth later.
나중에 더 깊이 알아보겠습니다
But for now,
지금으로선
let's just assume that we randomly assigned three different cluster centers.
클러스터 중심을 무작위로 놓았다고 가정하죠
If we're going to assume some, three means algorithm here.
3-means 알고리즘에서요
And then the first step is we're going to assign every observation
첫 단계는 모든 샘플을 가장 가까운
to the closest cluster center.
클러스터 중심에 할당하는 것입니다
So this observation here gets assigned to the red cluster.
이 샘플은 빨간색 클러스터에 할당되죠
These observations are all closest to the green cluster, or this green center here.
이 샘플들은 모두 초록색 클러스터, 초록색 중심에 할당됩니다
And these are all closest to the blue center.
이 샘플들은 모두 파란색 중심에 가깝고요
And a way to do this is something that's just called a Voronoi tessellation.
이를 위해서 보로노이 조각화란 기법을 씁니다
So we look at the cluster centers and well, we can do our define,
클러스터 중심으로 범위 설정도 할 수 있는데
let me switch again to this magenta color.
자홍색으로 다시 변환하죠
So here the cluster centers.
이것들이 클러스터 중심이죠
And we can just define these regions here.
여기 영역을 설정합니다
And these regions represent areas where any observation we might get,
영역은 새로운 샘플이 들어왔을 때
so any new observation, that's a very bad color on red.
빨간색에 쓰기 나쁜 색이네요
What other colors do I have?
다른 색이 뭐가 있었죠
How about white?
흰색은 어떨까요?
Cool, white.
좋네요, 흰색
So some new observation I get here, if it falls within this red region,
새로운 샘플이 들어왔을 때 이 빨간 영역에 속한다면
I know it's closest to this red cluster center.
빨간색 클러스터 중심에 가장 가깝다는 사실을 알 수 있습니다
So that's what these colored regions are representing.
이것이 색칠된 영역이 나타내는 바입니다
Okay so, that's the first step of the algorithm.
이게 알고리즘의 첫 단계였고요
So, what I end up with are observations that are assigned to clusters.
이로써 얻어지는 결과는 클러스터에 할당된 샘플이죠
But I just randomly initialize those clusters centers, so I probably don't
그런데 클러스터 중심을 무작위로 초기화했으니
believe that that really represents the structure underlying the data.
데이터에 잠재된 구조를 제대로 표현하고 있다고 생각하긴 힘듭니다
So what I wanna do is I wanna iterate this process, where I then wanna update what my
그래서 이 과정을 반복, 할당된 샘플을 기반으로
definition is of the cluster center based on the observations that I've assigned.
클러스터 중심을 재조정합니다
So if you remember this red cluster here,
여기 빨간색 클러스터에는
it just had one observation assigned to it.
샘플 하나만 할당되어 있었죠
So when I go to revise the cluster center for that cluster,
클러스터의 중심을 재조정하면
it just moves to the previous observation.
이전 샘플로 옮겨갑니다
But for this green cluster, if I look at the previous cluster center here,
초록색 클러스터의 경우 이전 클러스터 중심을
well I'm gonna move it to the center of mass of all
초록색 클러스터에 할당된
these observations that have been assigned to the green cluster.
모든 샘플의 무게중심으로 옮깁니다
And the center of mass of all of them is here,
모든 샘플의 무게중심은 여기니
so this becomes the new cluster center.
이게 새로운 클러스터 중심이 됩니다
And likewise, I do this for all of the blue observations.
모든 파란색 샘플에도 똑같이 적용합니다
This is the new cluster center for this blue observation.
이게 파란색 샘플들의 새로운 클러스터 중심이 되지요
Okay, so now I have a new set of cluster centers.
이게 새로운 클러스터 중심 집합입니다
And what I can do is redraw this Voronoi tessellation, and
이제 보로노이 다이어그램을 다시 그려
reassign my observations to the nearest cluster center.
샘플을 최근접 클러스터 중심에 할당합니다
And then I iterate this process until convergence.
이 작업을 수렴할 때까지 반복합니다
[MUSIC]
[음악]